<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home</title>
    <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 22:39:27 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.wbillingsley.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed studio teaching</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/distributedstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 22:39:27 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/distributedstudio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do we make a class full of remote students feel like they are working in a studio environment, collaborating on a software design journey together?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ongoing research since 2011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OLT grant for 2016 (to look at the student experience doing a critique process over asynchronous video)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011, while I was working at NICTA, Jörn Guy Süß and I designed a software studio course for UQ where we put the whole class working on one project. It was a &amp;ldquo;supercollaborative&amp;rdquo; course, as we had teams working on each feature, but because they worked on a common project the teams had to collaborate with each other. In 2012, I coordinated the course and refined it, together with Jim Steel. The following two years, Jim and I co-taught it as DECO2800 with Jim coordinating &amp;ndash; in 2014 we had 200 students on the same project, which we believe is still a record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I moved to UNE, where the vast majority of our students are remote. I&amp;rsquo;m quite keen on studio teaching &amp;ndash; it makes &amp;ldquo;I see what you did there&amp;rdquo; moments happen, and students can learn from each others&amp;rsquo; experiences not just their own. So, at UNE I created perhaps one of the first &lt;em&gt;distributed&lt;/em&gt; studio courses, and we had students from all over Australia, and even Hong Kong, working on a project together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Waugh put together a little a couple of little videos about it for our YouTube stream&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Note, the screenshots aren&amp;rsquo;t from the student code &amp;ndash; David grabbed some slides from an early lecture where I was encouraging students to think about the wide variety of game styles and mechanics they could be inspired by.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NnpW73thvAU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EO9NSg_yL5A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the students are never in the same room together, we are very reliant on CSCW systems &amp;ndash; both real-world ones (GitHub, Slack, etc) and custom ones I&amp;rsquo;ve created (Assessory so students can critique each other over video, and soon a project status dashboard). As Australia&amp;rsquo;s only &lt;em&gt;distributed&lt;/em&gt; studio development course, there&amp;rsquo;s rather a lot of research and work to do in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UNE version actually has slightly more content in it (at least compared to last time I taught the UQ version). That&amp;rsquo;s an interesting effect of having two mostly-online lectures per week versus one two-hour in-person session at UQ &amp;ndash; there is suddenly quite a noticeable demarkation between the content delivery and the studio practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects we had the students working on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2011 UQ - &lt;em&gt;RoboCode&lt;/em&gt; (using the open source code as a base) &amp;ndash; we gave a set of 30 different overlapping ways to change the game, and a continuous integration environment so the teams&amp;rsquo; code would have to work together&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2012 UQ - &lt;em&gt;RoboCode&lt;/em&gt; (again) &amp;ndash; this year we threw it over to students to decide how to change the game; one group turned it into robot soccer, and another added Call of Duty killstreaks &amp;hellip; This iteration was mostly about improving the student experience (replacing things that didn&amp;rsquo;t work), making the inter-team collaboration start earlier (at feature design rather than only after coding has begun), and adding a demo day and portfolios to give the students a clear view of how they&amp;rsquo;d be assessed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2013 UQ - &lt;em&gt;DECO Arcade&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; A Steam-like game arcade. Jim had the very good idea of giving students a smaller starter code-base, so they could own the architectural design as well as the features. (It turns out if you give students a large code base, they knit their code into it rather than making structural changes or refactoring). We also added a critique process, which I built into Assessory (over about four days), partly inspired by &lt;em&gt;Exegesis&lt;/em&gt;, an online &amp;ldquo;write, submit, then critique others&amp;rdquo; exercise Harriet Truscott had built in Cambridge for students of Shakespearian literature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2014 UQ - &lt;em&gt;Decoworld&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; I wrote the starter for this one, but the to be fair the mission was Jim&amp;rsquo;s idea &amp;ndash; DECO Arcade had been a too fragmented &amp;ndash; different teams doing different games, and sharing a few &amp;ldquo;hub&amp;rdquo; features. So let&amp;rsquo;s make it a single open world game so that the features will need to play with each other more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2015 UNE - &lt;em&gt;Decoworld&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; as I&amp;rsquo;d written the starter code for Decoworld, I re-used the same starter code at UNE as a way of comparing the UQ on-campus and UNE off-campus dynamics. Would studio work with off-campus students? This was also the first year I added Slack. (And it turned out Jim did at UQ too &amp;ndash; we shared materials, including me recording UQ&amp;rsquo;s exam practice tutorial video)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2016 UNE &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;Sense-O-Matic&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; We&amp;rsquo;re quite big on data science at UNE, so this year the students will be building a real-time data processing and visualisation platform (using Akka and JavaFX).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 UNE &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;Leaders&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; An empire-building game where the AI works for you. Partly inspired by playing too much &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mathstiles</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/mathstiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 22:39:27 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/mathstiles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>first</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:19 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/post/first/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will Billingsley</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:06 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a lecturer in the computational science group at the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.une.edu.au&#34;&gt;University of New England&lt;/a&gt;, where I research and teach
Human-Computer Interaction and Software Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a brief bio explaining how I came to be interested in HCI research from
a software development background on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wbillingsley.com/about&#34;&gt;About page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also the course coordinator for our &lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/courses/BCOMP&#34;&gt;undergraduate computer science degree&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;projects:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collaborative projects I&amp;rsquo;m part of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/distributedstudio/&#34;&gt;Technology for distributed studio teaching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of &amp;ldquo;studio&amp;rdquo; teaching styles where students can learn from each others&amp;rsquo; project experiences not just their own. In 2016, I have an OLT grant around supporting this style of teaching across distributed classes &amp;ndash; where most of the students are off-campus.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;with Bing Ngu, Huy Phan, Nicolas Gromik, and Paul Kwan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;past collaborations with Jim Steel and Jörn Guy Süß at UQ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ramselect.com.au/&#34;&gt;RamSelect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Sheep CRC developed a site to help graziers make use of sheep genetics information when selecting breeding rams, initially working with Telstra and Pivotal. This project has largely been around helping them build a small development team here at UNE to take the product forward.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;with the Sheep CRC, Paul Kwan, David Paul, and Johan Boshoff and his new team&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Livestock wellbeing data platform&lt;br /&gt;
This is a national effort involving rather a lot of people and organisations&amp;hellip; probably can&amp;rsquo;t say much more yet, except we&amp;rsquo;re going to find out a lot about designing interactive systems involving data science, combinations of very diverse models, and rolling data predictions&amp;hellip;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;with the Sheep CRC, Data2Decision CRC, Paul Kwan, David Paul, and many more&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;SMARTfarm learning hub&lt;br /&gt;
The SMARTfarm is one of UNE&amp;rsquo;s landmarks. Recently, Mark Trotter led a successful OLT grant application to bring data from the SMARTfarm more directly into UNE&amp;rsquo;s teaching in a number of areas. My involvement is in bringing live agricultural data into our studio and advanced web courses&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;part of Mark Trotter&amp;rsquo;s rather large team&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;MetaMood&lt;br /&gt;
David&amp;rsquo;s mostly managing this one (supervising a very capable student, Alec Shaw), but I&amp;rsquo;ve had some involvement in the design. Essentially this is a gamification app for health, related to Metabolic Syndrome. Initiated by Rhonda Wilson, the subject matter expert.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;with Rhonda Wilson, David Paul, Alec Shaw, and Paul Kwan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;plus a number of HCI side projects I&amp;rsquo;m not quite publicising yet (the BCompSc redesign has taken up a lot of my time)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-students:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Current Students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fun parts of my job is giving advice to students starting their research journey. My style is to be much more an advisor than a director &amp;ndash; fundamentally it&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;em&gt;student&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; PhD, so my goal is to help find them a path along the direction they want to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jaloud Aljaloud (PhD), with Paul Kwan and Nicolas Gromik, looking at designing student response apps for Saudi Arabian education&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salem Alamri (PhD), with Paul Kwan, looking at human computation&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Josh Henderson (Coursework masters thesis), looking at strategies for handling concurrency issues in systems designed around message-queues such as ActiveMQ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publications:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of my publications, please see any of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/William_Billingsley&#34;&gt;My profile on ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nicta.academia.edu/WilliamBillingsley&#34;&gt;My profile on Academia.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com.au/citations?user=ZvIsrJsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;My profile on Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But note they tend to lag a little. Like most academics, I&amp;rsquo;m not a regular gardener of my homepages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC220&#34;&gt;COSC220 Software Engineering Studio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC370&#34;&gt;COSC370 User Experience and Interaction Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC250&#34;&gt;COSC250 Programming Paradigms&lt;/a&gt;, with Matthew Cooper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC360&#34;&gt;COSC360 Advanced Web Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Former&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2015/units/COMP393&#34;&gt;COMP393 Software Project Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2015/units/COMP391&#34;&gt;COMP391 Advanced Web Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DECO2800 Design Computing Studio 2, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSSE3002 The Software Process, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSSE2003 Software Studio, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Materials for some of these (and some &amp;ldquo;catch-up&amp;rdquo; mini-units) will be published
publicly in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will&#39;s brief bio</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:06 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of getting interested in everything, so one way to explain my
interests is with a quick bio&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-phd:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Before PhD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, I graduated in Engineering from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uq.edu.au/itee&#34;&gt;UQ&lt;/a&gt;,
and went on to work on the core development team for what was the SingleView customer
care system. (The company I worked for has been bought many times and is now part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csgi.com/solutions/customer-interaction-management&#34;&gt;CSGi&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what I was doing was very solid software engineering, in C, Delphi, and
Java. But I started to become interested in interaction design because thought
the way enterprise software is customised by client teams is unnecessarily
cumbersome, and I was interested in using End User Programming techniques to improve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Later, I would realise that modern software development is an incredibly
elaborate Computer Supported Cooperative Work environment &amp;ndash; an almost ideal
playground for a technically-minded HCI researcher.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;phd:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;PhD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2000s, the chance came up to do a PhD with
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~pr10&#34;&gt;Peter Robinson&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~afb21&#34;&gt;Alan Blackwell&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/rainbow/&#34;&gt;interaction design
research group&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on the Intelligent Book project &amp;ndash; a joint project with MIT to develop
intelligent teaching systems, where students could work cooperatively
with AI, primarily interacting with diagrams, in a socially-constructed
textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great deal of fun on this project. A lot of the research was on making
AI &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; finding ways to translate between the user&amp;rsquo;s mental model and
the machine&amp;rsquo;s mental model (usually using the diagram as context). But I also
developed a drag-and-drop language for mathematics, ways of modeling complex
questions with very simple AI, and a better way to ask short answer questions on
the web. And on the technical side, this was modern web development (with async
communication to the server) before it was commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did rather a lot of student theatre, which probably helped my teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;caret:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;CARET&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I finished my PhD, I worked for the university for a little over a year,
on small development projects and also finding out what&amp;rsquo;s involved in taking
new technology from research into production. We didn&amp;rsquo;t entirely succeed &amp;ndash;
it was technology seeking a customer, and not even in a start-up context as it
was internal to the university. But it was a formative voyage of discovery, as I
had the chance to discover how entrepreneurialism is supposed to happen (even
if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t actually doing a start-up!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nicta:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;NICTA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, I moved to Brisbane to become a research engineer with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nicta.com.au/&#34;&gt;NICTA&lt;/a&gt;
(which has since been merged with part of CSIRO to form
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csiro.au/en/Research/D61&#34;&gt;Data61&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I was working on multi-modal
conversation analysis and visualisation &amp;ndash; if we took a video, could we throw
every kind of simple analysis we can think of at it
(topic-mapping, relevance-mapping, pause patterns and turn-taking from audio,
movement from video, etc),
and &amp;ldquo;see&amp;rdquo; what happened in the conversation before we watch the video back?
This was framed as an educational technology project, looking at how
to improve communication skills training for doctors, but was mostly creating
tools for data analysis, processing and visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-studio-teaching-nicta-uq:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Collaborative studio teaching (NICTA &amp;amp; UQ)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Jörn Guy Süß and I were asked to teach UQ&amp;rsquo;s software engineering studio
and project management units, after the unexpected death of David Carrington. We
were given leeway to make some changes to the software engineering unit, and
turned it into a &amp;ldquo;supercollaborative&amp;rdquo; studio &amp;ndash; each group of students developed
a different feature of the same product, so that not only were the students
collaborating in groups, the groups were collaborating with each other on a
common project. This proved successful, as it let us make the development process
in the course more closely match real-world software development, with continuous
integration, test-driven development, distributed version control, etc. In 2013,
Jim Steel and I turned this into Design Computing Studio 2, with better critique
processes and elements of continuous design in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, we had 200 students working concurrently on the same project &amp;ndash;
which we believe is a record. (In 2015, the student numbers went up again,
but the class was split across three projects.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;une:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;UNE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I moved to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.une.edu.au&#34;&gt;University of New England&lt;/a&gt;,
which was hiring a new small &amp;ldquo;computational science&amp;rdquo; team, but also wanted to
redesign its computer science degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, this meant a continuing (rather than fixed term) academic position,
the chance to help design a degree, and the opportunity to design
a &lt;em&gt;distributed&lt;/em&gt; studio course. Eighty per cent of UNE&amp;rsquo;s students study by distance education,
but we still want them to have the experience of studio teaching and collaborative development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran a trial of this in 2015, and it is becomming COSC220 Software Engineering Studio
from 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>