<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home</title>
    <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 22:39:27 +1100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.wbillingsley.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>mathstiles</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/mathstiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 22:39:27 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/projects/mathstiles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>first</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:19 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/post/first/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will Billingsley</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:06 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a lecturer in the computational science group at the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.une.edu.au&#34;&gt;University of New England&lt;/a&gt;, where I research and teach
Human-Computer Interaction and Software Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a brief bio explaining how I came to be interested in HCI research from
a software development background on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wbillingsley.com/about&#34;&gt;About page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also the course coordinator for our &lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/courses/BCOMP&#34;&gt;undergraduate computer science degree&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publications:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a list of my publications, please see any of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/William_Billingsley&#34;&gt;My profile on ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://nicta.academia.edu/WilliamBillingsley&#34;&gt;My profile on Academia.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com.au/citations?user=ZvIsrJsAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;My profile on Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But note they tend to lag a little. Like most academics, I&amp;rsquo;m not a regular gardener of my homepages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching:d680e8a854a7cbad6d490c445cba2eba&#34;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC220&#34;&gt;COSC220 Software Engineering Studio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC370&#34;&gt;COSC370 User Experience and Interaction Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC250&#34;&gt;COSC250 Programming Paradigms&lt;/a&gt;, with Matthew Cooper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2016/units/COSC360&#34;&gt;COSC360 Advanced Web Programming&lt;/a&gt;, with Matthew Cooper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Former&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2015/units/COMP393&#34;&gt;COMP393 Software Project Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://my.une.edu.au/courses/2015/units/COMP391&#34;&gt;COMP391 Advanced Web Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DECO2800 Design Computing Studio 2, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSSE3002 The Software Process, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSSE2003 Software Studio, UQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Materials for some of these (and some &amp;ldquo;catch-up&amp;rdquo; mini-units) will be published
publicly in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will&#39;s brief bio</title>
      <link>http://www.wbillingsley.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 21:27:06 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.wbillingsley.com/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of getting interested in everything, so one way to explain my
interests is with a quick bio&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-phd:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Before PhD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, I graduated in Engineering from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uq.edu.au/itee&#34;&gt;UQ&lt;/a&gt;,
and went on to work on the core development team for what was the SingleView customer
care system. (The company I worked for has been bought many times and is now part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csgi.com/solutions/customer-interaction-management&#34;&gt;CSGi&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what I was doing was very solid software engineering, in C, Delphi, and
Java. But I started to become interested in interaction design because thought
the way enterprise software is customised by client teams is unnecessarily
cumbersome, and I was interested in using End User Programming techniques to improve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Later, I would realise that modern software development is an incredibly
elaborate Computer Supported Cooperative Work environment &amp;ndash; an almost ideal
playground for a technically-minded HCI researcher.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;phd:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;PhD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2000s, the chance came up to do a PhD with
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~pr10&#34;&gt;Peter Robinson&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~afb21&#34;&gt;Alan Blackwell&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/rainbow/&#34;&gt;interaction design
research group&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on the Intelligent Book project &amp;ndash; a joint project with MIT to develop
intelligent teaching systems, where students could work cooperatively
with AI, primarily interacting with diagrams, in a socially-constructed
textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great deal of fun on this project. A lot of the research was on making
AI &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; finding ways to translate between the user&amp;rsquo;s mental model and
the machine&amp;rsquo;s mental model (usually using the diagram as context). But I also
developed a drag-and-drop language for mathematics, ways of modeling complex
questions with very simple AI, and a better way to ask short answer questions on
the web. And on the technical side, this was modern web development (with async
communication to the server) before it was commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did rather a lot of student theatre, which probably helped my teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;caret:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;CARET&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I finished my PhD, I worked for the university for a little over a year,
on small development projects and also finding out what&amp;rsquo;s involved in taking
new technology from research into production. We didn&amp;rsquo;t entirely succeed &amp;ndash;
it was technology seeking a customer, and not even in a start-up context as it
was internal to the university. But it was a formative voyage of discovery, as I
had the chance to discover how entrepreneurialism is supposed to happen (even
if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t actually doing a start-up!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nicta:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;NICTA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2009, I moved to Brisbane to become a research engineer with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nicta.com.au/&#34;&gt;NICTA&lt;/a&gt;
(which has since been merged with part of CSIRO to form
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csiro.au/en/Research/D61&#34;&gt;Data61&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially I was working on multi-modal
conversation analysis and visualisation &amp;ndash; if we took a video, could we throw
every kind of simple analysis we can think of at it
(topic-mapping, relevance-mapping, pause patterns and turn-taking from audio,
movement from video, etc),
and &amp;ldquo;see&amp;rdquo; what happened in the conversation before we watch the video back?
This was framed as an educational technology project, looking at how
to improve communication skills training for doctors, but was mostly creating
tools for data analysis, processing and visualisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborative-studio-teaching-nicta-uq:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Collaborative studio teaching (NICTA &amp;amp; UQ)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Jörn Guy Süß and I were asked to teach UQ&amp;rsquo;s software engineering studio
and project management units, after the unexpected death of David Carrington. We
were given leeway to make some changes to the software engineering unit, and
turned it into a &amp;ldquo;supercollaborative&amp;rdquo; studio &amp;ndash; each group of students developed
a different feature of the same product, so that not only were the students
collaborating in groups, the groups were collaborating with each other on a
common project. This proved successful, as it let us make the development process
in the course more closely match real-world software development, with continuous
integration, test-driven development, distributed version control, etc. In 2013,
Jim Steel and I turned this into Design Computing Studio 2, with better critique
processes and elements of continuous design in the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, we had 200 students working concurrently on the same project &amp;ndash;
which we believe is a record. (In 2015, the student numbers went up again,
but the class was split across three projects.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;une:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;UNE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I moved to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.une.edu.au&#34;&gt;University of New England&lt;/a&gt;,
which was hiring a new small &amp;ldquo;computational science&amp;rdquo; team, but also wanted to
redesign its computer science degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, this meant a continuing (rather than fixed term) academic position,
the chance to help design a degree, and the opportunity to design
a &lt;em&gt;distributed&lt;/em&gt; studio course. Eighty per cent of UNE&amp;rsquo;s students study by distance education,
but we still want them to have the experience of studio teaching and collaborative development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran a trial of this in 2015, and it is becomming COSC220 Software Engineering Studio
from 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>